Burd-Shippen Papers 1708-1792 Mss.B.B892
American Philosophical Society
Burd-Shippen Papers
1708-1792
Mss.B.B892
American Philosophical Society
2.5 Linear feet 12 volumes
James Burd (1726-1793) was well-known in colonial Pennsylvania through his role in the French and Indian War, as well as his connections to many of the colony's leading families (most notably the Shippen family). Initially starting out as a merchant in Philadelphia, Burd became increasingly involved with colonial affairs after moving to Lancaster County with his family in 1752. It would be on the frontier where Burd would make his mark first as a soldier, and later as a magistrate. The Burd-Shippen Papers consist mainly of letters and business documents sent to James Burd, with the bulk of the collection relating to the French and Indian War, 1754-1763, in which Burd served as an officer commanding troops at Fort Augusta and elsewhere. The 2.5 linear feet in the collection reflects all aspects of Burd's life in Pennsylvania as a merchant, soldier, and magistrate; as well as his involvement with the Shippen family professionally and personally. Intermixed with items sent to Burd are receipts to his wife Sarah Shippen Burd, and correspondence between Edward Shippen and James Hamilton regarding land matters and Indian affairs in Lancaster.
Burd, James, 1726-1793
Bibliography
Nixon, Lily Lee. James Burd, Frontier Defender, 1726-1793. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1941. Call No. 920.0748 P38 no. 4
Gillingham, Harrold E. "Notes on the Burds of Ormiston, Scotland and Philadelphia." Philadelphia: Genealogical Society of Pennsylvania, 1939. Call No. 920 Pam. v.49, no.4
Hunter, William A. Forts on the Pennsylvania Frontier, 1753-1758. Harrisburg: The Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission, 1960. Call No. 974.8 H915f
Early American History Note
This collection is one of the largest early American collections the APS holds. Its breadth of sources provides insight into colonial Pennsylvania history, especially that of Lancaster County. Although largely material composed of material from James Burd, there are also significant documents relating to the Shippen family. Documents touch on matters financial, political, and social. While the collection is of wide ranging material, its strength lies in three main parts: the Seven Years’ War and Pontiac’s Rebellion in Pennsylvania, Burd’s business records, and life in Lancaster County from 1754-1776.
The first, largest, and perhaps most significant portion of the collection are the records relating to the Seven Years’ War and Pontiac’s Rebellion. This aspect of the collection consists of numerous letters written to Burd or that Burd had in his papers from other officers, soldiers, and officials. All aspects of the Seven Years’ War and Pontiac’s Rebellion are discussed in these documents, ranging from the political to the military to the social effects of the war. It should be noted that the collection contains few of Burd’s actual letters, but instead has letters to him or one of the Shippens, or between others. Moreover, most of these letters are from high ranking officers to other officers or officials, and thus often reflect high level concerns about provisioning, orders, or other military matters.
Burd also left behind one of the most complete accounts of a Pennsylvania fort during this period. Burd left receipt books, account books, orderly books, quartermaster records, muster rolls, and other material surrounding the operation of Fort Augusta. Some of this material is in this collection; other parts are in the Fort Augusta collection and Samuel Hunter Collection.
Finally, the collection has diaries from the war. These accounts convey the day-to-day happenings of an officer in the western Pennsylvania during this period, although the entries are not very detailed. These diaries include one from western Pennsylvania, one from Fort Augusta, and one from the Siege of Fort Henry. There are also fragments of diaries in the “Letters” portion of the collection.
The second theme of this collection is the wide-ranging and shifting financial affairs of James Burd. In particular, the collection has a series of account books that reflect Burd’s business dealings as a merchant in Philadelphia before the war, as a spirits distributor in Lancaster County after the war, and finally as a farmer. Burd was a prominent merchant in Philadelphia and his account books from when he opened a shop in 1747 until he left in about 1752 are contained at the collection at the APS. These three volumes offer a nearly complete picture of his business operations during this phase of his life. The account book from his spirits shop in Lancaster spans from 1765-1768 and is likewise nearly complete. Finally, the receipts from the postwar period capture his transition from merchant to prominent and active farmer in the Pennsylvania hinterland. Combined, these records offer a portrait of three different but common occupations in colonial Pennsylvania. The collection captures someone who moved from merchant in a seaport to a military officer to a merchant in a backcountry town to a farmer. Rarely are such documents as complete and even rarer, are they for a single individual.
The third significant part of the collection provides information on politics and society in Pennsylvania, particularly the backcountry and Lancaster County. There are a number of letters between Edward Shippen and James Hamilton, a colonial governor and large landowner, about the affairs of Lancaster during the Seven Years’ War and the American Revolution. There are also papers relating to the creation of the Lancaster Library Company (later named Juliana after Thomas Penn’s wife) and Shippensburg Library Company. Letters from officials, particularly those of Captain Lewis Curry at Fort Bedford, occasionally describe the state of backcountry inhabitants. The large receipt collection also provides insight into trade in the backcountry.
The collection has a surprisingly small amount of records relating to Native-American-white relations. The Journal from 1760 includes treaty minutes and accounts of interactions with Indians, especially with Shikellamy. A letter from John Armstrong discusses tensions over land rights and again makes frequent mention of Shikellamy. There are also smatterings on women’s experiences during the war, particularly as sutlers.
Letters: The letters focus on the Seven Years’ War. There are some letters from before the war and some from after, but the focus is on the Seven Years’ War. The letters from before and after the Seven Years’ War often relate to the family’s commercial interests in Philadelphia and Lancaster. Of particularly note are a series of letters from Joseph Shippen, the secretary of the provincial council from 1762-1776, written in the 1780s that involve settling the Penn family’s outstanding financial concerns.
Letters from the Seven Years’ War are predominantly about military affairs during the war and focus on James Burd’s service, although most letters were not written by Burd. Information on road construction, the creation and disestablishment of the provincial army, military maneuvers throughout Pennsylvania, and provisioning are all contained in these letters. A notable portion of letters is from Edward Shippen, whose exchanges with Governor James Hamilton help describe the situation of Lancaster during the war.
Miscellaneous Papers: These papers are also heavily focused on the Seven Years’ War. Again, documents from before the war focus on trade and business. There is also a meteorological diary James Burd kept in 1747.
The Seven Years’ War documents again include details on the Pennsylvania military, although these tend to focus on Fort Augusta and include information on manning, supplies, and provisioning. There is three years (1756-1758) worth of morning and evening reports. There are also miscellaneous lists of regiments and enlistments, including interesting details, such as height, origin, of birth, trade, on enlistees’ backgrounds that may be of interest to historians.
For material after the war, there is a detailed outline of James Burd’s proposed garden and a detailed letter on the boundary dispute between Pennsylvania and Virginia in what is today western Pennsylvania.
Receipts and Account Books: As with the rest of the collection, the most significant portion of the receipts comes from the Seven Years’ War. But there are also a large number of receipts from the 1740s relating to James Burd’s personal and business purchases.
The contents of the receipts over time tend to trace the changes in Burd’s own financial interests. The early Philadelphia receipts reflect those of a typical merchant, while those in the later period reflect those of a farmer in western Pennsylvania.
Of note, there are three volumes of James Burd’s account books from 1747-1749 in the collection, which are very detailed. Joseph Shippen used the back pages of some of these volumes for his own commonplace book from 1810-1820. There is also a pocket-sized personal account of James Burd from 1756-1758 and numerous account books from Fort Augusta in both this collection and the Fort Augusta Collection. Also of note, there is also an account book from 1765-1768 from Lancaster for the period that James Burd operated a spirits shop.
Printed Forms: The collection houses a single large volume of printed forms. These are almost all records of enlistments, but earlier ones deal with Burd as Philadelphia merchant. The enlistments contain data on enlistees’ name, size, occupation, and place of birth that may be of interest to genealogists and social historians, among others.
Diaries: There are three diaries in this collection. One is from 1760 and surrounds the construction of Fort Burd and expeditions throughout western Pennsylvania. The diary includes references to ongoing Native-white interactions, both peaceful and violent.
Another diary is from 1763 during Burd’s time at Fort Augusta. It recounts the opening of Pontiac’s Rebellion and the initial reports of the Indian raid on the Connecticut settlers in the Wyoming Valley.
The third diary is a six-page handwritten journal of Siege of Fort William Henry that contains an account of the events of the capitulation and surrender of that British fort to the French and their Indian allies.
Related Archival Materials note
Additional collections at the American Philosophical Society Library relating to the Burd-Shippen familes and their part in early Pennsylvania and Philadelphia history and the French and Indian War include: The Edward Shippen Papers (B Sh62), Edward Shippen's receipts (B Sh621) and docket of cases (973.2/H91r), the Joseph Shippen waste book (657 Sh6), the Joseph Shippen, Jr. letterbook (B Sh62.j), the William Shippen, Jr journal (B Sh61) and prescription book (B Sh61.1), the Shippen Family Maps (649.962 Sh6m), and Shippen Family Papers (B Sh6lf).
For those interested in the French and Indian War (particularly material related to garrisons and logistics), the Library holds the Fort Augusta account books (973.2/B89o & rD54;F77a,d,1), and the Fort Pitt cash book (973.2 F78c). Additional documentation on the French and Indian War can be found in the Timothy Horsfield Papers (974.8 H78).
Additional material relating to the Burd and Shippen families can be found at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, the University of Delaware Library Special Collections Department, and the William L. Clements Library at The University of Michigan.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Unknown.
Scope and Contents note
The Burd-Shippen Papers consist mainly of letters and business documents sent to James Burd, with the bulk of the collection relating to the French and Indian War, 1754-1763, in which Burd served as an officer commanding troops at Fort Augusta and elsewhere. The 2.5 linear feet in the collection reflects all aspects of Burd's life in Pennsylvania as a merchant, soldier, and magistrate; as well as his involvement with the Shippen family professionally and personally. Intermixed with items sent to Burd are receipts to his wife Sarah Shippen Burd, and correspondence between Edward Shippen and James Hamilton regarding land matters and Indian affairs in Lancaster.
This collection is an ideal source for those studying either the logistical aspects of the French and Indian War, or mercantile matters in colonial Pennsylvania. The earlier correspondence relates primarily to matters of business: notices of sales, requests for payments, bills of lading, and management of Burd's properties. While the French and Indian War material is comprised mainly of logistical matters (supply, payment of troops, muster rolls), there are a number of letters that discuss garrison conditions, troop movements, and Indian affairs in addition to the diaries and journals in Series IV. Garrison life and logistics, as well as business, are covered in the other three series of the collection.
Items of particular interest include the correspondence between Edward Shippen and James Hamilton relating to matters in Lancaster. Shippen regularly kept Hamilton informed of the use of land, requests for timber from Hamilton's property, and other matters. Additionally, the letter between Joseph Shippen, Jr. and John Penn dated 1788 November 1 is of particular interest for its documentation of fees and taxes collected by the colonial government prior to the Revolution.
The material is organized into four series (correspondence, miscellaneous material, receipts, and bound volumes), with each series arranged chronologically. The bound volumes of Series IV each have a unique call number, which is necessary to reference when requesting this material. One of the items, a copy of a journal kept at the siege of Fort William Henry, 2-10 August 1757 (973.2/F77) was sent to Burd, and has been printed in I. Minis Hays, "The Siege of Fort William Henry," Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, vol. 37 (1898): 143.
Series I. Correspondence 1740-1792 1 linear foot
Series II. Miscellaneous Items 1708-1791 .75 linear feet
Series III. Receipts 1746-1792 .75 linear feet
Series IV. Bound Volumes 1747-1787 12 volumes
Biographical/Historical note
James Burd (1726-1793) was well-known in colonial Pennsylvania through his role in the French and Indian War, as well as his connections to many of the colony's leading families (most notably the Shippen family). Initially starting out as a merchant in Philadelphia, Burd became increasingly involved with colonial affairs after moving to Lancaster County with his family in 1752. It would be on the frontier where Burd would make his mark first as a soldier, and later as a magistrate.
Born at Ormiston Hall near Edingburgh, Scotland on March 10, 1726, James Burd was one of Edward Burd and Jean Haliburton's ten children. Little is known about Burd's youth in Scotland, though it seems he received a very thorough education. Upon reaching adulthood, Burd left Scotland and spent a year in London before arriving in Philadelphia in September 1747. It did not take him long to become established in the city, quickly making business and social connections. Within his first year he was renting a store on Front Street, advertising in the Pennsylvania Gazette, a member of the Presbyterian Church, and a member of the St. Andrews Society of Philadelphia. Through either his social activities or membership in the church Burd came into contact with several of Philadelphia's prominent families -- including those of Shippen, Willing, and Allen. That first year he also became romantically involved with Edward Shipppens's daughter Sarah, and the two were married in 1748.
Burd's business endeavors continued to grow in Philadelphia. By the end of 1748 he had moved his store to Carpenter's Wharf, his younger brother John was indentured to him in 1749, and his brother-in-law Joseph Shippen was working in the store. In 1750 Burd expanded his business involvement into the shipping world, becoming a partner in the snow, Sally. Finally, Burd sought to further extent his mercantile business with a trip to Jamaica in 1751, entrusted with merchandise worth over a thousand pounds. Unfortunately the trip proved to be a failure as a hurricane hit the island and wrecked many of his investments. The year proved additionally bad for Burd as his business in Philadelphia began to decline after he made too many investments and over extended credit to his customers.
Leaving the mercantile business, Burd took up farming and milling on land provided by his father-in-law in Lancaster County. In 1752 he moved his family west to Shippensburg, on the Pennsylvania frontier. With the outbreak of the French and Indian War Burd began his long career of public service to the colony. James' first appointment came in March 1755 when Governor Robert Morris named him one of five commissioners (along with George Croghan, William Buchanan, John Armstrong, and Adam Hoops) to survey a supply road from Shippensburg to Raystown for General Edward Braddock's Expedition against Fort Duquesne. That April Burd was placed in charge of building the road. Unfortunately, the work progressed too slowly to be of any assistance, and the work was abandoned after Braddock's army evacuated to Philadelphia.. Afterwards Burd remained in western Pennsylvania fortifying the frontier. In December 1755, Burd was commissioned a captain with orders to build and command a fort at Kishicoquilas -- which was later named Fort Granville. The following April, Burd was promoted to major in the Third Battalion (or Augusta Regiment) and sent with his troops to command Fort Augusta. On January 2, 1758 Burd was promoted to lieutenant colonel of the Second Battalion of the Pennsylvania Regiment after Colonel Conrad Weiser resigned. With this promotion Burd was put in command of a large stretch of territory including several forts from the Susquehanna River to the Delaware River in addition to his duties at Fort Augusta. That year Burd assisted with the construction of Fort Ligonier, and the following year built Fort Burd on the Monogahela with James Shippen. Following the Treaty of Lancaster in 1762, Burd was named one of the commissioners to receive prisoners brought to Fort Pitt, and in 1763 was appointed a commissioner and justice of the peace to negotiate with Connecticut in order to prevent the further settlement at Wyoming on land belonging to the Six Nations. Burd continued to command at Fort Augusta until he resigned from the army in 1765.
Upon returning to his family, who had spent the last ten years living in Lancaster, Burd sought to build a new home. In 1767 he purchased a 500 acre tract of land along the Susquehanna River in what is now Lower Swartara Township, and began construction of a stone house he named Tinian. The following year he moved his family into Tinian, where he remained for the rest of his life. Burd continued in public service, serving as Justice of the Peace and Magistrate for the Courts of Lancaster County. Additionally, he was chairman for the county's Committee for the Relief of the Boston Sufferers in 1774, and in 1775 was elected to the Lancaster County Committee of Safety. With the outbreak of the Revolution, Burd actively supported the cause for independence, helping to raise troops in Lancaster County. Although he was commissioned a colonel he never commanded troops in the field, and resigned in 1776. Burd continued to serve as a magistrate in Lancaster County until his death on October 5, 1793.
Armstrong, John; Atlee, Samuel John, 1739-1786; Barkley, Thomas; Bond, Phineas, 1749-1815; Bouquet, Henry, 1719-1765; Buchanan, William; Burd, Sarah Shippen, 1731-1784; Coxe, William; Croghan, George, d.1782; Graydon, Caleb; Hall, David, 1714-1772; Hambright, John; Hamilton, James, 1710-1783; Harris, John, 1726-1791; Hunter, Samuel; Lardner, Lynford, 1715-1774; Logan, James, 1674-1751; McCormick, Dennis; Mercer, Hugh, 1726-1777; Miles, Samuel, 1740-1805; Morgan, John,1735-1789.; Ourry, Lewis, 1717-1779; Peters, Richard, 1704-1776; Shippen, Edward Jr.; Shippen, Edward, ca. 1703-1781; Shippen, Joseph Jr.; Shippen, Joseph; Stirling, Walter; Swan, Hugh; Tilghman, James, 1716-1793; Trent, William, 1715-1787?; Wister, Daniel, 1739-1805; Young, James; Business and Skilled Trades; Business Records and Accounts; Colonial Politics; Diaries; Family Correspondence; Fort Augusta (Pa.); Fort Duquesne; Fort Hunter; Fort Pitt (Pa.); Fort William Henry (N.Y.); General Correspondence; Government Affairs; Iroquois Indians; Lancaster County (Pa.)--History; Land and Speculation; Meteorology--Pennsylvania--Observations; Military History; Miscellaneous; Native America; Official Government Documents and Records; Pennsylvania --History --French and Indian War, 1755-1763; Pennsylvania History; Pennsylvania--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Commerce; Political Correspondence; Seven Years' War; Shippenburg Library Company; Surveying and Maps; Trade; Travel Narratives and Journals; United States--History--French and Indian war, 1755-1763; United States. Army. Supplies and stores
- Correspondence, 1740-1792; Series I; 1 lin. foot
  Scope and Contents note
  Letters to Burd from Edward Shippen of Lancaster, Henry Bouquet, John Hambright, Lynford Lardner, Samuel Miles, William Trent, Walter Stirling, Daniel Wister, and others, on personal and business matters.
  - to Edward Shippen, 1740 October 27; 1p.; Hendrix, James (Box 1)
    Donnegall. Sending few skins he has, and hope for more in spring.
  - to James Hamilton, 1742 February 10; 3pp.; Cooks, Thomas (Box 1)
    Lancaster. Regarding Roger Hunt's sale of property and request for a new deed, George Gibson's interest in purchasing two lots, and the issue of the town charter regarding the raising of money.
  - to James Burd, 1747/8 March 21; 1p.; Walsh, Janet (Box 1)
    Philadelphia. Regarding the sale of three boxes of china for Burd, and Walsh's share in the sale.
  - to Lynford Lardner, 1748 October 20; 1p.; Shippen, Edward Jr. (Box 1)
    Philadelphia. Has received money via James Burd to purchase gun in London.
  - to Johannes Kern, 1749 January 1; 3pp.; Barkley, Thomas (Box 1)
    Three copies of one page notice of a set of bills drawn and due.
  - to Johannes Kern, 1749 January 2; 1p.; Barkley, Thomas (Box 1)
    Notice of a bill drawn and due.
  - to Johannes Kern, 1749 December 29; 3pp.; Barkley, Thomas (Box 1)
  - to Johannes Kern, 1749 December 30; 3pp.; Barkley, Thomas (Box 1)
    Three notices of bills drawn and due.
  - to Johannes Kern, 1749 December 30; 1p.; Barkley, Thomas (Box 1)
  - to James Burd, 1750 January 2; 1p.; Hollingsworth, John (Box 1)
    Paxton. Request that a warrant be issued agains Jno. Foster, Jr. for oats.
  - to James Burd [maybe Kern?], 1750 January 4; 1p.; Barkley, Thomas (Box 1)
    Notice he has drawn funds payable in London.
  - Indenture, 1749 - 1750 January 13; 2pp.; Burd, John (Box OS)
    Indenture to his brother James in Philadelphia.
  - to James Burd, 1750 March 3; 1p.; Philip, Robert (Box 1)
    Philadelphia. Request for pay to Charles Buchan.
  - to Capt. Edward Dowers, 1750 March 9; 1p.; Barkley, Thomas (Box 1)
    Philadelphia. Asks that Dowers apply to Burd for his route to Maryland and to take any items Burd wishes loaded on the Marlbourough.
  - to Burd & Swift, 1750 June 8; 1p.; Hill & Lamar (Box 1)
    Notice of sale of items sent by Burd and Swift, and the balance brought over.
  - to James Burd, 1750 August; 1p.; Barkley, Thomas (Box 1)
    Maryland. Inquiring regarding the sale of items.
  - to James Burd, 1750 September 5; 1p.; Freid, John (Box 1)
    Regarding purchase of servants [?] in New Castle. [Fragment?].
  - to James Burd, 1750 November 12; 1p.; Allyne, Samuel (Box 1)
    Requests Burd's assistance in business matters.